A Guide to the YMCA of Greater Richmond Records, 1854-2019 (bulk 1920-1998)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
YMCA of Greater Richmond Records, 1854-2004 (bulk 1920-1998)
Library of Virginia
41642
35.5 cu. ft. (67 boxes and 1 oversize folder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of YMCA of Greater Richmond, December 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Young Men's Christian Association was created on 6 June 1844 in London, England, by George Williams. The organization was formed to provide young, working men of the Industrial Revolution a safe haven to participate in healthy activities. At the Great Industrial Exposition of 1851 in England, British YMCA members passed out flyers and encouraged visitors to start chapters in their home countries. By 1855, 329 YMCA's were in operation in nine nations. The first North American YMCA began in November 1851 in Montreal and the first YMCA in the United States opened December 1851 in Boston.
On 19 December 1854, the Richmond YMCA was founded, electing Peter V. Daniel, Jr., as their first president. The headquarters opened May 1855 at the Goddin Building, at Bank and 11th Street in Richmond facing Capitol Square. The organization focused on providing a safe home for young men of the city, building a library, and offered lectures, devotional meetings, and Bible classes.
By 1882 the Richmond YMCA was the nation's sixth largest YMCA. It drew members to numerous programs, classes, and lectures and its ever expanding library. To accommodate the growing organization, the Richmond YMCA built its first building on Sixth and Main Street, complete with a bowling alley, gym, library, classrooms, and lecture hall. One of the most popular activities were the sports and fitness programs, embracing the idea of "muscular Christianity."
The African-American community became involved with the YMCA when in 1887 the Richmond Colored Young Men's Christian Association was formed. In 1889 the Richmond Colored YMCA became the first African-American YMCA to own its own facility, located on East Leigh Street in Jackson Ward (Leigh Street YMCA). Reverend John Milton Waldron was the first YMCA's executive director and Reverend Scott C. Burrell served as secretary. The YMCA's remained segregated until 1965 when it agreed to accept "all qualified applicants to membership without regard to race, color or creed."
In 1910 the YMCA expanded and opened a new building on Seventh and Grace Streets, with the area's first YMCA pool. In 1942 the YMCA moved to its present day location on East Franklin and North Foushee streets. Throughout the world wars the YMCA was involved in wartime bond drives and welcoming soldiers to the facilities. The YMCA also encouraged the involvement of women and children in the organization. With the explosion of the suburban lifestyle in the 1950's, the Richmond YMCA provided youth programs on a massive scale and created suburban branches to serve the population. The South Richmond Branch became the first Y suburban outpost and was established in 1955.
Throughout the 1970-1990's the Richmond YMCA expanded into several other neighborhoods including Chesterfield, Chickahominy, Downtown, North Richmond, Patrick Henry, Shady Grove, and Tuckahoe. In 2004 there were over 12 branches in Richmond and Petersburg and the counties of Chesterfield, Goochland, Hanover, Henrico, and Powhatan. These branches annually help over 128,000 members and non-members and have a staff of over 1,400. The YMCA of Greater Richmond focuses on providing a place for members of the community to enrich their lives and achieve their fullest potential in spirit, mind, and body.
For a more in-depth history of the YMCA of Greater Richmond, consult the book, on which these records were based and gathered: "The Richmond YMCA 1854-2004" by Edward R. Crews (YMCA of Greater Richmond, 2004).
Scope and Content
The YMCA of Greater Richmond Records, 1854-2019, are housed in 67 boxes and arranged into seven series. Series have been designated for I. Annual reports and Minutes, II. Research files- Chronological, III. Research files- Subject, IV. Newspaper clippings and scrapbooks, V. Photographs, VI. YMCA Library, and VII. Artifacts. The records include annual reports, by-laws, constitutions, correspondence, deeds, library books, memorials, minutes, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs, programs, publications, reports, research notes, and vouchers. These records document the history of the YMCA in Greater Richmond and the organizations work within the community.
The records were created during the research and publication of the anniversary book entitled, "The Richmond YMCA 1854-2004," by Edward R. Crews. This collection does not portray the records as they were housed by the organization, but rather the manner in which they were organized for the publication of the book. It is important for researchers to note this artificial arrangement because its use has caused much overlap between the series. It is therefore important that researchers cross-check subjects, dates, and events to yield all the information on a particular topic. Since the material is described at the folder level, researchers should have little problem finding these links.
While the collection contains some earlier annual reports, newsletters, photographs, and programs, the majority of the records are from the mid to late 20th century. Of note is Series V: Photographs, 1854-2019. Some of the earliest known photographs can be found here, along with a large selection of photographs of YMCA members at various social and sporting events from the 1920's to the 1960's. Similar to the Research series, the Photograph series is subdivided into chronological and subject subseries.
The Research files (Series II and III) contain the bulk of the materials used during research for the anniversary book. The files were maintained in their original order, with some files arranged chronologically and others by subject. Therefore, as with the rest of the collection, there is much overlap between the two series. Again, researchers must cross-check both series to find all related materials. For example annual reports, by-laws, brochures, and newsletters can be found in both series. The chronological files contain more 19th century documents, while the subject files contain more 20th century documents. The subject files also contain research notes and rough drafts for the anniversary book.
A more in-depth description of the collection can be found in the series level description. It is recommended that the researcher read the series level scope and content notes thoroughly before accessing the collection.
Series I: Annual reports and Minutes, 1905-2002 (bulk 1954-2002)
The Annual reports and Minutes are housed in 12 boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title. The annual reports, 1954-1991, consist mainly of typed unpublished financial reports submitted by the member associations (Richmond) to the National Council of the YMCA. These reports include information on population, membership statistics, salaries, expenditures, and income. (Published annual reports can be found in Series II and III.) The financial summaries, 1956-1979, include budgets and monthly financial details. The minutes include Board of Directors Minutes, 1929-2001, Boys' Bible Study Club Minutes, 1905-1909, and Camp Richmond Minutes, 1935-1947. The minutes contain board of directors membership lists, certificates of incorporations, dormitory statistics, policies, reports, resolutions, and treasury reports.
Series II: Research files- Chronological, 1855-2004
The Research files- Chronological are housed in 6 boxes and arranged chronologically by decade. Included are annual reports, brochures, checkbooks, clippings, constitutions, correspondence, newsletters, programs, reports, and vouchers. The original filing system used by the YMCA History Committee was maintained as much as possible. The items in each chronological file were arranged by a system of numbers and alphabets and many folders contain note cards highlighting specific documents. It was assumed that a research assistant of the YMCA History Project Committee had a key for arranging these materials, but that key was not discovered.
Included are numerous publications: Constitution and By-laws, 1855; Catalgoues of the Library, 1859-1876; "Discourse on the Ethics of Christianity," 1855; "The Southern Church Justified In Its Support of the South in the Present War," 1863; "Richmond YMCA Statistics," 1893; "The Beautiful Building of the YMCA," 1896; "Men, Morals Money," 1904; "Virginia Railway and Power Company YMCA Report," 1912; "Ten Years of Progress," 1937; "Richmond's Home Fires: The Story of the Richmond YMCA," 1942; "Your YMCA Keeping Pace with a growing Richmond area," 1969; and "Nourishing the Spirit, the Mind, and the Body," 1989.
Also included are miscellaneous published annual reports, 1856-2000, and newsletters such as the Association Branch of Church Hill, 1883-1888, Young Mens' Friend of the Colored YMCA of Richmond, 1890- 1900, Monthly Messenger, 1903-1904, Richmond's Young Men, 1900-1960, Richmond Railroad Men, 1909-1917, and Y News, 1960-2000. Of note are the various programs for anniversary celebrations, building dedications, conferences, memorials, and entertainment programs for the Richmond YMCA. Included are several reports on visits by members of the national YMCA branches to Richmond, specifications on buildings, and reports on YMCA clubs such as the Railroad Men and the Woodrow Wilson Senior Hi-Y Club. Also included are brochures and pamphlets advertising the Richmond YMCA, Colored YMCA, and Railroad YMCA organizations. These are of special interest because they highlight the work being performed by the YMCA, along with information on dues, programs, and classes available to members.
Series III: Research files- Subject, 1854-2004 (bulk 1965-1995)
The Research files- Subject are housed in 9 boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title. This series is similar to the Chronological files and there is much overlap between the two series. Included are agreements and deeds, files on the various Richmond YMCA branches, newsletters, publications, drafts and research notes for the book.
Of note are the numerous agreements and deeds, 1884-1977, for the YMCA buildings in Richmond (Sixth and Main St. and Seventh and Grace Sts.) and Camp Richmond (Charles City, Virginia). The agreements and deeds folders contain appraisals, correspondence, financial reports, incorporation papers, insurance papers, lists of articles placed in the building cornerstone, subscriptions to the building fund, and title abstracts. Also of note is a sketch of the early history of the Richmond YMCA, written c. 1890, by an unknown author.
The branch files contain information on the various Richmond YMCA branches: Chester, Chickahominy, Downtown, Manchester, Midlothian, North Richmond, Patrick Henry, Shady Grove, Southside and Tuckahoe. Included are clippings, correspondence, deeds, fundraising campaigns, histories, membership lists, newsletters, photographs, press releases, program guides, promotional materials, reports, and surveys dating mostly from 1965-1995. Of note are the program guides and histories written for each local chapter.
Publications include "A Study of the YMCA Richmond Central Branch," 1970; centennial program for the North Richmond Branch, 1987; "Memories of my association with the last Dr. Scott C. Burrell, Secretary of Colored YMCA, Richmond," 1946 (includes marriage certificate of Burrell); and "Real Estate Appraisal of Patrick Henry YMCA," 1995.
Also included are copies of the newsletter Richmond's Young Men, 1901-1953, and annual reports, 1960-1964 and 1994-2002. Most importantly, the series includes biographies, chronology, committee members notes, correspondence, drafts, notebooks, notes, and proposals for the book "The Richmond YMCA 1854-2004: 150th Anniversary."
Series IV: Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks, 1910-2003 (bulk 1988-2001)
The Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks are housed in 14 boxes and are arranged chronologically. Included are clippings mainly from the Richmond Times Dispatch and other local Richmond newspapers such as the Chesterfield Gazette, Henrico/Hanover Plus, Hanover County Herald-Progress, Progress Index, and the Richmond News Leader. Topics include the opening of new YMCA branches, anniversary celebrations, activities and festivals, summer camp, capital campaigns and expansions, board appointments, work with the Richmond city government, programs, opening of the YMCA to women, tournament scores, and elections of officers. Also included are 7 scrapbooks, containing mostly clippings dating from 1910-1988 (bulk 1960-1985).
Series V: Photographs, 1854-2019 (bulk 1950-1990)
The Photographs are housed in 13 boxes and arranged into 6 subseries. Subseries have been designated for Chronological; Branches; Staff; Subject files; Slides, Cds, and Oversize; and Presidents. As with the paper records, all of the photographs were original source materials used in research for the book, "The Richmond YMCA 1854-2004: 150th Anniversary." This series contains a wide variety of photographs of Board members, facilities, members, and staff. Of note are the numerous photographs of members attending social and sporting events, ranging from 1920-1990. There are few, if any, photographs from the pre Civil War era, mostly reproduction photographs of annual reports and sketches of Civil War scenes. Included are photographs of Board members and staff from the 1940's and 1990's. Unfortunately many of the later staff photographs are unidentified.
Subseries 1: Chronological, 1854-2004 (bulk 1910-1990)
The Chronological photographs are housed in 7 boxes and arranged chronologically by decade. This subseries includes some of the most interesting photographs in the collection. Although there are folders for the earliest years, 1854-1870, they only include reprint photographs of the first annual report, an artist reproduction of the first YMCA meeting in 1844, and a Civil War drawing. The images from the 1880's and 1900's include some of the earliest photographs of YMCA buildings, facilities, and members. Throughout the 1920-1960 era are a variety of photographs of members at the health club and social and sporting events. The 1960's also include photographs of the boys and girls Northside Day Camp, along with numerous sporting events. The photographs from the 1980's include a group of publicity photographs for the facilities of the YMCA branches, such as Downtown, North Richmond, South Richmond, and Tuckahoe.
Subseries 2: YMCA Branches, 1950-2001 (bulk 1990-2000)
The YMCA Branches photographs are housed in 3 boxes and arranged alphabetically by branch name. Included are photographs for the following branches: Chester, Chickahominy, Downtown, Manchester, Midlothian, North Richmond, Patrick Henry, Petersburg, Shady Grove, and Tuckahoe. Also included are photographs of Camp Thunderbird in Chesterfield, Virginia. Of note are photographs of dedications and groundbreaking for the various branches, holiday parties, golf tournaments, and other social activities.
Subseries 3: Staff, 1940-2000 (bulk 1980-1990)
The Staff photographs are housed in 3 boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title. Included are photographs of various management, staff, and Board members. The Board members and management photographs are well identified, but most of the staff photographs are unidentified.
Subseries 4: Subject files, 1970-2000
The Subject file photographs are housed in 2 boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title. Included are photographs of children, group shots, Heritage Club celebrations, Indian Guides, YMCA Kinder Kollege, self defense classes, teens, and miscellaneous unidentified photographs.
Subseries 5: Slides, Cds, and Oversize, 1880-1998 (bulk 1980-1998)
The Slides, Cds, and Oversize photographs are housed in 8 boxes. The oversize photographs include a framed photograph of the General Secretaries of the YMCA of Richmond, 1880-1937, photograph of the Business Mens Bible Class, 1925, and posterboards depicting various events at the YMCA, c. 1980. Many of the posterboard and other oversize photographs are reproductions and enlargements of photographs housed in one of the other subseries. The cds are all images scanned for the anniversary book. The slides include images of sports, camp, fitness, gymnastics, various slideshows on the YMCA history, new employee orientation, and images from various facilities including Chester, Chickahominy, Downtown, Midlothian, North Richmond, Patrick Henry, Shady Grove, and Tuckahoe.
Subseries 6: Presidents and Chairs, 1955-2019
The Presidents and Chairs photographs are housed in 1 box. Photographs are of the men and women who have served as president or chair of the YMCA between 1955 and 2019
Series VI: YMCA Library, 1906-2004
The YMCA Library consists of over 80 books published by the YMCA, housed in a lending library in the YMCA or volumes used during the research of the book by Edward R. Crews. Of note are the YMCA Yearbook and Official Roster and Directories, 1932-2002, and the Statistical Summary and Analysis, 1982-1999. Included are numerous books on the history of the national and international branches of the YMCA, service of the YMCA during war time, story of the Railroad Y, and history on the founders of the YMCA. Also included are various books on the history of the Civil War and researching skills.
Series VII: Artifacts, 1979-2000
The Artifacts include several plaques, t-shirts, and a flag.
Arrangement
Arranged into 7 series: I. Annual reports and Minutes, II. Research files- Chronological, III. Research files- Subject, IV. Newspaper clippings and Scrapbooks, V. Photographs, VI. YMCA Library, and VII. Artifacts.
Contents List
- Series I: Annual reports and Minutes, 1905-2002 (bulk 1954-2002), 4.2 cu. ft. (12 boxes); Boxes 1-12.
  - Annual reports, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual reports, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual reports, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual reports, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual reports, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual reports, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual reports, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual reports, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual reports, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual reports, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual reports, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual reports, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual reports, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual reports, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual reports, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annual reports, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Annual reports, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Annual reports, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Annual reports, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Annual reports, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Annual reports, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Annual reports, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Annual reports, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Annual reports, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Annual reports, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Annual reports, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Annual reports, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Annual reports, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Annual reports, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Annual reports, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Annual reports, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Financial summaries, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Financial summaries, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Financial summaries, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Financial summaries, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Financial summaries, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Financial summaries, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, The Boy's Bible Study Club, 1905-1908 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, Endowment Fund, 1961-1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, Metropolitan Board, 1929-1930 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, Committee of Management, 1934-1935 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, Metropolitan Board and Camp Richmond, 1936-1937 and 1935-1948 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1946-1950 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1989 January-June (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1989 July-December (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1991 January-June (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1991 July-December (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1994 Part 1 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1994 Part 2 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1994 Part 3 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1995 Part 1 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1995 Part 2 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1996 Part 1 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1996 Part 2 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1996 Part 3 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1997 Part 1 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1997 Part 2 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1998 Budget (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1998 Part 1 of 2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1998 Part 2 of 2 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1999 Budget (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1999 January-June (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1999 July-December (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 2000 Budget (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 2000 January-April (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 2000 May-June (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 2000 July-December (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 2001 January-June (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 2001 July-December (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 2001 Annual plan (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 2002 Annual plan (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series II: Research files- Chronological, 1855-2004, 2.1 cu. ft. (6 boxes); Boxes 13-18.
  - Early history research notes (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1855-1859 Documents (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
  - 1855-1859 Research notes (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 1860-1869 Documents (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 1860-1869 Research notes (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 1870-1879 Documents (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 1870-1879 Research notes (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - 1880-1889 Documents (Box 13, Folder 9-11)
  - 1890-1899 Documents (Box 14, Folder 1-4)
  - 1900-1909 Documents (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
  - 1900-1909 Research notes (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - 1910-1919 Documents (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
  - 1910-1919 Research notes (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - 1920-1929 Documents (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - 1930-1939 Documents (Box 15, Folder 3-4)